<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8445 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8445.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-holmberg-mmusic-ice-premature-latest" obsoletes="" updates="8445" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ICE Premature">
      Prevent Premature Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) Failures
    </title>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
  
    <date year="2019"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>MMUSIC Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>ICE</keyword>
    <keyword>Candidate</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        ...
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC8445"> describes a protocol, Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE), 
        for Network Address Translator (NAT) traversal for UDP-based communication.
      </t>
      <t>
        When an endpoint receives the initial set of candidates from the remote peer, it starts to
        process them. As part of the processing, one or more candidates might get discarded. There
        are a number of reasons why a candidate is discared, e.g., because it represents an IP version
        that is not supported by the endpoint, or if the connection-address associated with the candidate
        is represented by a Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) that the endpoint is not able to resolve.
        Similairly, as a candidate by definition represents a single connection-address, if a FQDN 
        resoles into multiple connection-addresses the associated candidate needs to be discared. 
      </t>
      <t>
        NOTE: Future specifications might describe how FQDNs that resolve into multiple connection-addresses
        are used with ICE.
      </t>
      <t>
        According to the procedures in <xref target="RFC8445">, if an endpoint discards the complete set
        of initial candidates received from the remote peer, it will declare an ICE failure, and terminate
        the session establishment, as the endpoint's list of remote candidates will be empty.
      </t>
      <t>
        Once the endpoints have exchanged the initial set of candidates, and start performing connectivity 
        cheks, additional candidiates might be created as a result of the connectivity checks. Such candidates
        are referred to as peer relexive candidates. However, the endpoint will most likely have declared
        ICE failure before it is able to create such candidates.
      </t>
      </t>
      <t>
        This speicifcation updates <xref target="RFC8445">, by suggesting that an endpoint does not immediately
        declare ICE failure in case the initial set of candidiates received from the remote peer are
        discarded, but instead wait for a while in case it will receive connectivity checks that create one
        or more peer reflexive candidates. Once the endpoint has created such candidates, it processes them
        using the normal procedures defined in  <xref target="RFC8445">.
      </t>
    </section>
 
    <section title="Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Update to RFC 8445">
      <t>
        ...
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section.sec" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
          The security considerations for ICE are defined in <xref target="RFC4566" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
          This specification only recommends ICE endpoints to wait for a certain time of period before they declare
          ICE failure, and does not introduce new security considerations.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA considerations">
      <t>
        This specification makes no requests to IANA.
      </t>

    <section anchor="sec-acks" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
      <t>
        ...
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8445"?> 
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
